I am a researcher in Human-Computer Interaction, Human Factors Engineering and Health Informatics. My primary interest is informing the design of tools that assist in decision making, particularly those that use sophisticated computation. I engage in empirical research and design efforts with a goal of generating new knowledge and theory about computer-supported decision making.

## **Education**

#### 2015 PhD, Media and Information Studies

Michigan State University

Advisor: Rick Wash

Committee: Gary Hsieh, Joshua Introne, Wei Peng, Emilee Rader, Joseph B.

Walther

#### 2010 MSI, Human-Computer Interaction

University of Michigan

Advisor: Mark Newman

Committee: Stephanie Teasley

#### 2007 BS, Psychology

University of Utah

Certificate in Human Factors Engineering

#### 2007 BA, Russian

University of Utah

## **Positions**

#### **Research Positions**

#### 2015 - Present Postdoctoral Fellow

University of Michigan Medical School

Center for Bioethics and Social Sciences in Medicine

Mentor: Brian Zikmund-Fisher

#### 2010 - 2015 **Graduate Research Assistant**

Michigan State University

Behavior, Information, Technology Lab

#### 2010 Research Associate

University of Michigan

Comprehensive Cancer Center

#### 2008 - 2009 Research Associate

University of Michigan Medical School

Open.Michigan

#### 2008 Research Associate

University of Michigan Library

Usability Working Group

## **Teaching Position**

#### 2008 - 2009 Graduate Student Instructor

University of Michigan

Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures

## **Publications**

#### **Theses**

2015 Decision Biases in User Agreement with Intelligent Decision Aids

**Doctoral Dissertation** 

Michigan State University

2010 Real-Time Text and IM

Master's Thesis

University of Michigan

#### Peer-reviewed publications

**Note.** Proceedings papers in the top HCl conferences such as CHl and CSCW are rigourously peer-reviewed and have the most prestige and impact in the field.

2016 p.12 Heterogeneity in Customization of Recommender Systems Among Users with Homogenous Preferences

Jacob Solomon

Proceedings of the 2016 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) [23% acceptance rate]

2016 p.11 Highly Successful Projects Inhibit Coordination on Crowdfunding Sites

Jacob Solomon, Wenjuan Ma, Rick Wash

Proceedings of the 2016 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) [23% acceptance rate]

2016 p.10 Is This Good or Bad? Redesigning Visual Displays of Medical Test Results in Patient Portals to Provide Context and Meaning

Jacob Solomon, Aaron M. Scherer, Nicole L. Exe, Holly O. Witteman, Angela Fagerlin, Brian J. Zikmund-Fisher

Proceedings of the 2016 CHI Conference Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) [43% acceptance rate]

2015 p.9 Don't Wait! How Timing Affects Coordination of Crowdfunding Donations

Jacob Solomon, Wenjuan Ma, Rick Wash

Proceedings of the 18th ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW) [28% acceptance rate]

# 2015 p.8 Factors Related to Privacy Concerns and Protection Behaviors Regarding Behavioral Advertising

Donghee Yvette Wohn, Jacob Solomon, Dan Sarkar, Kami Vaniea

Proceedings of the 33rd Annual ACM Conference Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) [43% acceptance rate]

#### 2014 p.7 Customization Bias in Decision Support Systems

Jacob Solomon

Proceedings of the 32nd Annual ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) [23% acceptance rate]

#### 2014 p.6 Coordinating Donors on Crowdfunding Sites

Rick Wash, Jacob Solomon

Proceedings of the 17th ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW) [27% acceptance rate]

Best Paper Honorable Mention

#### 2014 p.5 Critical Mass of What? Exploring Community Growth of WikiProjects

Jacob Solomon, Rick Wash

Proceedings of the 8th International AAAI Conference on Weblogs and Social Media (ICWSM) [23% acceptance rate]

#### 2014 p.4 Human-What Interaction? Understanding User Source Orientation

Jacob Solomon, Rick Wash

Proceedings of Human Factors and Ergonomics Society Annual Meeting 58(1) 422-426

Best Paper Nominee

# 2012 p.3 Bootstrapping Wikis: Developing Critical Mass in a Fledgling Community by Seeding Content

Jacob Solomon, Rick Wash

Proceedings of the 15th ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work [40% acceptance rate]

# 2010 p.2 Speaking Through Text: The Influence of Real-Time Text on Discourse and Usability in IM

Jacob Solomon, Mark Newman, Stephanie Teasley

Proceedings of the 16th ACM International Conference on Supporting Group Work (GROUP) [36% acceptance rate]

#### 2007 p.1 Digital Photo Kiosk Evaluation

Jacob Solomon, Frank A. Drews

Human Factors and Ergonomics Society Annual Meeting 51(5) 484 - 488

### **Conference Abstracts (lightly peer-reviewed)**

#### 2016 a.6 Improving Understanding of Test Results by Substituting (Not Adding) Goal Ranges

Aaron M. Scherer, Holly O. Witteman, *Jacob Solomon*, Nicole L. Exe, Angela Fagerlin, Brian J. Zikmund-Fisher

Society for Medical Decision Making Annual North American Meeting

# 2016 a.5 Providing Harm Anchors in Visual Displays of Test Results Mitigates Patient Concern About Nearly Normal Values

Brian J. Zikmund-Fisher, Aaron M. Scherer, Holly O. Witteman, *Jacob Solomon*, Nicole L. Exe, Angela Fagerlin

Society for Medical Decision Making Annual North American Meeting

# 2016 a.4 Understanding and Promoting Shared Decision Making with a Novel Interactive Online Tool

Fred Amell, *Jacob Solomon*, Brian Zikmund-Fisher, Konstantin Boroda, Yaara Zisman Ilani, Caroline Park, Santiago M. Thibaud, Anand D. Jagannath, Frederik Yick, Tina Shah, Taylor Miller, Ramachandra Reddy, Joshua Cho, Michelle Pong, Shey Mukundan, Esther Mizrachi, Ashley Ceniceros, Manaf Assafin, Hamid Lari, Kenny Ye, Darlene Lefrancois

Society of General Internal Medicine Annual Meeting

# 2016 a.3 A Novel Interactive Icon-Array Software Improves Comprehension of Absolute Risk in Medical Trainees and Helps Transform a Large Risk Communication Site into a Potent Resource for Shared Decision Making

Fred Amell, *Jacob Solomon*, Brian Zikmund-Fisher, David Newman, Caroline Park, Yaara Zisman-ilani, Konstantin Boroda, Santiago Thibaud, Anand Jagannath, Frederik Yick, Tina Shah, Taylor Miller, Ramachandra Reddy, Joshua Cho, Michelle Pong, Shey Mukundan, Kim Renwick, Esther Mizrachi, Darlene Lefrancois

4th Annual Lown Institute Conference

**Audience Choice Award** 

# 2013 a.2 Flaming, Criticism and Appreciation on Social Media - An Analysis of Discourse on YouTube Videos

M. Laeeq Khan, Jacob Solomon

National Communication Association (NCA)

#### 2013 a.1 Advocacy, Entertainment and News: An Analysis of User Participation on YouTube

M. Laeeq Khan, Jacob Solomon

Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC) Annual Conference

#### **Working Papers and Under Review**

#### 2011 u.1 Bots on Wikipedia: An Exploration of Social Influences

Jacob Solomon

Working Paper

#### **Technical Reports**

#### 2010 r.9 Evaluation of Comprehensive Cancer Center Patient Site

Jacob Solomon, Ricardo Yi

Technical Report for University of Michigan Comprehensive Cancer Center

#### 2009 r.8 Microsoft OneNote Tagging Comparative Evaluation

Jonathan Cohen, Umanka Karkada, *Jacob Solomon*, Janani Sundar Technical Report for Microsoft Corporation

#### 2009 r.7 Microsoft OneNote Tagging User Survey

Jonathan Cohen, Umanka Karkada, *Jacob Solomon*, Janani Sundar Technical Report for Microsoft Corporation

#### 2009 r.6 Microsoft OneNote Tagging Usability Testing

Jonathan Cohen, Umanka Karkada, *Jacob Solomon*, Janani Sundar Technical Report for Microsoft Corporation

#### 2008 r.5 OER Usability Analysis

Jacob Solomon

Technical Report for Open.Michigan

#### 2008 r.4 MTagger Usability Testing

Matthew Schultz, Jacob Solomon

Technical Report for University of Michigan Library Usability Working Group

#### 2008 r.3 MTagger Cognitive Walkthough and Heuristic</

Jacob Solomon, Matthew Schultz

Technical Report for University of Michigan Library Usability Working Group

#### 2008 r.2 MTagger User Interviews

Matthew Schultz, Jacob Solomon

Technical Report for University of Michigan Library Usability Working Group

#### 2008 r.1 MTagger Guerilla Testing of the Pop-up Tagging Window

Matthew Schultz, Jacob Solomon

Technical Report for University of Michigan Library Usability Working Group

## **Other Contributions**

#### 2016 Colonoscopy Screening Decision Aid

Designed and developed a tool with Dr. Sameer Saini of the VA to assist clinicians in deciding when to stop screening patients for colorectal cancer. This tool is available at http://das.med.umich.edu/screening/screening.html

## **Presentations**

Presented papers for publications c.1, c.2, c.3, c.4, c.5, c.6, c.7, c.9, c.11, c.12 at their respective conferences.

# Nov 19, 2015 Designing the Information Cockpit: The Impact of Customizable Algorithms on Computer-Supported Decision Making

Center for Bioethics and Social Sciences in Medicine Seminar

Ann Arbor, MI

#### Apr 25, 2014 Customization Bias in Decision Support Systems

Media and Information Studies Spring Research Symposium

East Lansing, MI

#### Apr 19, 2013 Crowdfunding Risks and Rules

Media and Information Studies Spring Research Symposium

East Lansing, MI

#### Apr 13, 2012 An Immediacy-Based Model of Source Orientation

Media and Information Studies Spring Research Symposium

East Lansing, MI

## **Awards**

#### 2014 Dissertation Completion Fellowship

College of Communication Arts and Sciences, Michigan State University

#### 2014 Outstanding Doctoral Researcher

Department of Media and Information Studies, Michigan State University

#### 2014 Best of Symposium Award

Media and Information Spring Research Symposium, Michigan State University

#### 2013, 2012 Summer Research Fellowship

College of Communication Arts and Sciences, Michigan State University

#### 2012, 2010 Travel Award

Department of Telecommunications, Information Studies, and Media, Michigan State University

#### 2009 Rakham Graduate Student Research Grant

Rackham Graduate School, University of Michigan

# **Teaching**

## **Courses Taught**

Fall 2008, Fall 2009 Russian 201

University of Michigan

Primary instructor for 3rd semester Russian language course

Winter 2009

Russian 202

University of Michigan

Primary instructor for 4th semester Russian language course

Winter 2008

Russia Today

University of Michigan

Led discussion sections, graded essays for undergraduate course on contemporary Russian culture and politics

Mentoring

2013, 2014

Katie Hoban

Mentored REU project on crowdfunding, contributed to papers c.9 and c.11

2012

Kyle Safran

Mentored REU project on crowdfunding, led to paper c.6

2012

Nate Zemanek

Mentored NSF Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) project on computer security

**Service** 

2016

Program Committee Associate Chair

ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI) - Late Breaking Work

2016 CBSSM Professional Development Committee Member

2014-16 Reviewer

ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)

Excellent Review Acknowledgement 2016

2013, 2015-17 Reviewer

ACM Conference on Computer-Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW)

2011 Reviewer

Journal of Computer-Mediated Comminication

# Membership

Association for Computing Machinery (ACM)

Human Factors and Ergonomics Society

Last updated: August, 2016